<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blindness on Devin Prater’s Site</title>
    <link>https://devinprater.github.io/tags/blindness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blindness on Devin Prater’s Site</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 07:28:35 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://devinprater.github.io/tags/blindness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>VoiceOver Recognition</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/voiceover-recognition/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 07:28:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/voiceover-recognition/</guid>
      <description>Introduction At the launch of the iPhone 3GS, Apple unveiled VoiceOver on the iPhone. Blind users and accessibility experts had been used to screen readers on computers, and even rudimentary screen readers for smart phones that used a keyboard, trackball, or quadrants of a touch screen for navigation and usage. But here was a screen reader that not only came prepackaged on a modern, relatively inexpensive to the competition, and off-the-shelf device, but it also allowed the user to use the touch screen as it is, a touch device.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching Tools</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/switching-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 21:57:53 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/switching-tools/</guid>
      <description>This is basically a test post. I&amp;rsquo;ve switched from Emacs to VS Code, and I&amp;rsquo;ll detail why below. The gist is that Emacs is unhelpful, only easy to set up on Mac and Linux, and Emacs packages are not standard, and Emacspeak, the speech extension for Emacs, just can&amp;rsquo;t keep up with extensions like LanguageTool, and probably won&amp;rsquo;t because coding is Emacs&#39; main use case, not writing.
Why I used Emacs Emacs has been my work tool for about a year now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brighter Apple</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-04-21-a-brighter-apple/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 12:15:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-04-21-a-brighter-apple/</guid>
      <description>Coding has always been hard for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve never been able to get my mind around loops, if and else, for and while, and break almost breaks me instead of the code. However, many people make it look easy, and for them, it probably is. In iOS 14, Apple may loosen their chains upon their technology enough for developers to explore the boundaries of what a pocket computer can do.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing Richly</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-04-16-writing-richly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 01:47:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-04-16-writing-richly/</guid>
      <description>Whenever you read a text message, forum post, Tweet, or Facebook status, have you ever seen some one surround a word with stars, like *this*? Have you noticed some one surround a phrase with two stars? This is Markdown, a form of formatting text for web usage.
I believe, however, that Markdown deserves more than just web usage. I can write in Markdown in this blog, I can use it on Github, and even in a few social networks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple’s Ecosystem and Accessibility</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-03-27-apple-ecosystem/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 16:40:55 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-03-27-apple-ecosystem/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this year, my Airpods Pro began making a clicking sound, when in Noise Cancellation or transparency mode. I didn’t think much of it, and just used them regularly, until sound began distorting after a while of listening. I’ve simply stopped using them, as I shudder to think how much a cab ride to the nearest Apple Store, potentially an hour away, would cost. This is only one problem with the Apple ecosystem: being locked into Apple’s wireless headphones, other Bluetooth headphones, or other workarounds, and Apple Stores being far away, which is what I’ll be focusing on in this article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>quick apple update</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-03-03-quick-apple-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 03:43:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-03-03-quick-apple-update/</guid>
      <description>In a [previous blog post]({% link _posts/2020-02-13-accessibility-consistency.md %}), I talked about Apple having a few problems to fix. Last month, they fixed one of them, being Apple Research. The hearing study now will have accessible hearing tests and questions. Focus is still a little jumpy in the Heart and Movement study questions, and my watch screen has become a moving part so I can’t participate in that study completely, or track my sleep accurately, but getting transportation to the Apple Store is something I’ve covered well on Twitter already.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>text formatting for the blind</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-23-text-formatting-for-the-blind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 13:46:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-23-text-formatting-for-the-blind/</guid>
      <description>Text formatting is used in many areas, from books, newspapers, articles, websites, and documents. Paragraphs, headings, lists, italics, bold, and many other characteristics are used to emphasize, denote chapters, and mark changes in scenes or actions. Sighted users can use formatting to find points of interest in text. What about people who are blind? Is formatting effective for us? Can it be useful?
In this article, I will explore text formatting, and how blind people use it or dismiss it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>legally blind</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-20-legally-blind/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 03:35:06 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-20-legally-blind/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever downloaded a file that you didn’t have permission to get? I have, many times in the past. This post, about copyright issues faced by blind people, may spark much debate in our community, but I feel that it must be written. It will cover games, books, films, and software which blind people copy, the justifications for doing so, and the harm that it can cause.
Introduction It was said, about 50 years ago, that some 70 percent of blind people are unemployed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>open source blindness</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-16-open-source-blindness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 20:11:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-16-open-source-blindness/</guid>
      <description>What if all of your software were free, like NVDA? What if the only thing asked of you by software makers was to donate or contribute? How would this effect your life, and the lives of developers? In this article, I will explain what open source is, what it is currently used for, my experiences with it, and how you can make it better.
What is Open Source? Open source is a splinter of the Free Software movement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple’s accessibility consistency</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-13-accessibility-consistency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 15:13:23 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-02-13-accessibility-consistency/</guid>
      <description>This article will explore Apple’s consistent attention to accessibility, and how other tech companies with commitments to accessibility, like Microsoft and Google, compare to Apple in their accessibility efforts. It also shows where these companies can improve their consistency, and that no company is perfect at being an Assistive Technology provider yet.
Introduction Apple has shown a commitment to accessibility since the early days of the iPhone, and since mac OSX Tiger.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advocacy of open source software</title>
      <link>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-01-20-advocacy-of-open-source-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://devinprater.github.io/2020-01-20-advocacy-of-open-source-software/</guid>
      <description>In this post, I’ll detail my experiences of advocating for accessibility in open source software, why it is important, and how others can help. I’ve not been doing it for long, but at least now, I’ve done a bit. I’ll also touch upon why I think open source software, on all operating systems, is important, and what closed source and closed feedback systems cannot offer, which open source grants. On the other hand, there are things which closed source somewhat grants, but which has faltered slightly in recent days.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
