<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Devin's Site (Posts about open-source)</title><link>https://devinprater.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://devinprater.github.io/categories/open-source.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:r.d.t.prater@gmail.com"&gt;Devin Prater&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License BY-NC-SA"
style="border-width:0; margin-bottom:12px;"
src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/88x31.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 04:12:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>open source blindness</title><link>https://devinprater.github.io/posts/2020-02-16-open-source-blindness/</link><dc:creator>Devin Prater</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;What if all of your software were free, like NVDA? What if the only
thing asked of you by software makers was to donate or contribute? How
would this effect your life, and the lives of developers? In this
article, I will explain what open source is, what it is currently used
for, my experiences with it, and how you can make it better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Open Source?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is a splinter of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software_movement"&gt;Free Software
movement&lt;/a&gt;. The
Free Software movement believes that everyone should be able to view a
program's code, and modify it if needed. The thing which sets open
source apart is that it doesn't mind working with companies which create
closed source, or proprietary, software which cannot be modified or have
its source code seen by the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When free and open source spokespeople talk about freedom, they mean
free as in free speech, not as in free things. This talk of freedom
upsets business, so the term "open source" is used instead. Much open
source software is free of cost, with the developers asking for donation
instead of demanding payment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Open Source used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source software is just about everywhere, and often comes with a
tightly knit community of users. Examples of open source in the blind
community include &lt;a href="https://www.nvaccess.org/about-nvda/"&gt;NVDA&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.libreoffice.org"&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects/Orca"&gt;Orca Screen
Reader&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://brailleblaster.org"&gt;Braille
Blaster&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://liblouis.org"&gt;Liblouis&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href="https://github.com/tvraman/emacspeak"&gt;Emacspeak&lt;/a&gt;. Examples of
closed source include &lt;a href="https://www.freedomscientific.com/products/software/jaws/"&gt;JAWS for Windows&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/help/17173/windows-10-hear-text-read-aloud"&gt;Narrator&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/accessibility/iphone/vision/"&gt;VoiceOver&lt;/a&gt;, the latest
version of
&lt;a href="https://support.google.com/accessibility/android/answer/6283677?hl=en"&gt;TalkBack&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://duxburysystems.com"&gt;Duxberry Braille translator&lt;/a&gt;, iOS, Windows, and plenty of apps you may have on
your iPhone or Android phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, some projects are a mixture of both. JAWS incorporates
Liblouis for braille translation, and so do Narrator and VoiceOver.
Apple uses plenty of open source tools: Python, command line shells, and
many command line tools on MacOS. Microsoft makes BRLTTY and Liblouis
available for download to interface with Narrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux, which founded many offshoots, is an entire operating system built
on open source ideals. Blind people began customizing Linux for use with
speech, and work is ongoing to make Linux an accessible operating
system. This began with &lt;a href="https://wiki.vinuxproject.org"&gt;Vinux&lt;/a&gt;. It
started up talking, something no other system had done before. One could
use it with speech or braille, and used the eSpeak voices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That operating system, or distribution of Linux as they are called, is
now abandoned, not having been updated in years. Another project, &lt;a href="https://distrowatch.com/table.php?distribution=sonar"&gt;Sonar
Gnu Linux&lt;/a&gt;, also
came and went. It was based on Arch Linux, and was my favorite
distribution. People now use &lt;a href="https://talkingarch.info/download.html"&gt;Talking
Arch&lt;/a&gt;, or
&lt;a href="https://tarch.org"&gt;Tarch&lt;/a&gt;, if they are adventurous and &lt;a href="https://slint.fr/wiki/doku.php?id=en:installation"&gt;Slint
Linux&lt;/a&gt; if they
aren't. These are the most popular Linux distributions for those who are
blind. If I've missed anything, let me know. Some distributions which
were not made for the blind are also accessible.
&lt;a href="https://getfedora.org"&gt;Fedora&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://trisquel.info"&gt;Trisquel&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.debian.org"&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://ubuntu.com"&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; are
also able to be installed, but the user must know the correct keyboard
command to turn on the screen reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most open source software can be found on &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;.
That's where NVDA, Orca, and many other tools, even for the blind, are.
But how reliable are these tools? What about the operating system? Could
one get rid of Windows with this software founded on ideals?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;My experiences with Open Source&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Linux&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is a software issue, so the root of software, the
operating system, will make or break any accessibility. My experiences
with Linux began, mainly, with an old operating system called
&lt;a href="https://wiki.vinuxproject.org"&gt;Vinux&lt;/a&gt;. I didn't stick with it for long,
and soon forgot about it, and it is now abandoned. Linux can run many
different desktops, which give users the major system functions of
accessing apps and system utilities. Gnome and Mate are accessible, just
about everything else, for now, including KDE, isn't. Vinux used Gnome
2, which is basically what Mate is now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came back to Linux for a short while with Sonar. I really liked it,
but missed the games and speech options Windows had. I liked all the
software that we have access to on Windows, and browsing the Internet
with Linux wasn't that good back then. I soon got into the Apple
ecosystem with an iPhone and such, and already had a Mac for quite a
while. Still, Linux called to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm never satisfied with the workflow I have. I always want to be more
efficient, more quick, more capable in what I do. I always want better
sound, even if 3D effects and virtual surround sound aren't actually
necessary or real. Like a sighted person wants great graphics, I want
great sound. On Linux, there is a way to enable virtual surround sound,
but it offers little reward, and much configuration, crackling in audio,
and doesn't augment stereo audio as options on other systems does. The
Mac has a third-party option, &lt;a href="https://www.globaldelight.com/boom/"&gt;Boom
3D&lt;/a&gt;, and Windows has &lt;a href="https://www.windowscentral.com/how-use-windows-sonic-windows-10-creators-update"&gt;Windows Sonic
for
Headphones&lt;/a&gt;.
Both of these require nearly no configuration, augments much more audio,
and only Boom 3D causes a bit of sluggishness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also want a faster way of doing things. Many keyboard shortcuts,
letter navigation of items in lists and menus, and ways of only getting
the information I want. I have much of this on the Mac, with the Mail
app allowing me, through table navigation, to speed through subjects
instead of having to hear the row titles and contents and all before
what I really want to hear, and being able to go to the previous or next
message in a thread without needing to close the window. Linux has some
of this, but many times things are unclear, with Orca, the Linux screen
reader, just speaking the items, and not what type of item it is. This
is clear in the area of Audacious settings where you choose sound
effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even so, Linux has such an appeal to me. I have tried Fedora Linux,
&lt;a href="https://slint.fr/wiki/doku.php?id=:en:start"&gt;Slint&lt;/a&gt;, Ubuntu, Debian, Arch, and found that there is always something
missing. Accessibility isn't that good in the graphical interface, and
much still takes a lot of configuring and asking the community. And I
really hate asking for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, the &lt;a href="https://mate-desktop.org"&gt;Mate desktop&lt;/a&gt; team has
released a version with accessibility fixes. This is important, as
many companies, like app developers, Apple, and Google, rarely share
that there are accessibility fixes in minor updates, and don't even
share all the new features in major releases. This gives me some hope
that the open source community at large just needs more blind people
telling them about our needs. Then again, this is probably just
another of my excuses to bash my head against the hardened wall of
Linux, yet again. Plus, everything in the open source moves slowly,
and this is doubly true for open source assistive technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are, however, blind people who use Linux, just as there are some
in the blind community who use Android. In fact, there is an entire
&lt;a href="https://linux-a11y.org"&gt;Linux Accessibility Site&lt;/a&gt;. However, the site
does have links to abandoned software, and doesn't link to all
accessibility initiatives, like &lt;a href="https://stormux.org"&gt;Stormux&lt;/a&gt;. Both
Linux-a11y and Stormux ask for donations, so there is also duplicated
effort and decentralization even in the blind Linux user community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I use a Mac. It contains enough open source technology to support
&lt;a href="https://brew.sh"&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Package_manager"&gt;package
manager&lt;/a&gt;. I can run
Emacs, with Emacspeak on it, along with just about any command line
program I'd use on Linux. The Mac's graphical interface is good enough
for mail and some web browsing, just not so good with Google Docs, and I
can probably do anything on it that a Linux user can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, sometimes, Linux calls to me still. VoiceOver isn't the best
screen reader out there, and Linux has the appeal of being run by
people, not corporations. And yet, looking at the &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/accessibility/accessibility.en.html"&gt;GNU accessibility
statement&lt;/a&gt;,
you'd think it was updated in 2006 or so. It may have been, which is a
slap in the face for any accessibility advocate. The GNU project, with
this statement, says to us that we're only worth putting up a quick
page, detailing the inaccessibility of old technologies and not
maintaining it. It tells us that we're a good poster to hang up in their
trophy room of "people aided by our courageous stand for the minorities
who desperately need our help," but then discarded for the "community"
to handle. After all, the GNU don't know anything about helping the
blind, do they? Can the GNU be expected to enforce accessibility among
their projects? Doesn't the government take care of the poor blind
people? Blind people have their Vinux and Sonar, why not just use those?
No, that is definitely not segregation, not at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Open Source Programs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began using NVDA around high school. No one had ever heard of it at
that point, in a day when people called all screen readers either "JAWS"
or "Microsoft." I've not stopped using it ever sense. Its features have
grown, its users growing even faster. It now has a community of
programmers, translators, and writers. It is, in my opinion, the most
versatile Windows screen reader. JAWS still works okay for some things,
like malformed spreadsheets, but for everything else on Windows, I use
NVDA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Braille Blaster is also a great project, making braille translation,
embossing, and transcription free. I use it for translating EBooks into
good, formatted braille files for reading on my iPhone using the BARD
Mobile app. Now, I don't even use Duxberry, even though it is provided
on my work computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've found that open source programs, built upon closed source operating
systems, are the best compromise. NVDA, BrailleBlaster, TDSR, and many
other tools built for the blind community run on Windows or Mac. Having
a great foundation in accessibility makes all the difference for users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How can You help?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Github, as stated earlier, is a hub of open source projects. One great
thing about the service is that anyone can contribute. Just make an
account, and you're ready to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can program, you can &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/github/collaborating-with-issues-and-pull-requests/creating-a-pull-request"&gt;collaborate by modifying
code&lt;/a&gt;.
If you try the software and find accessibility problems, you can tell
developers about &lt;a href="https://help.github.com/en/github/managing-your-work-on-github/creating-an-issue"&gt;bugs or
features&lt;/a&gt;
that need fixing or adding. If you find a project you like, they may
have a Patreon to which you can donate, or you can simply spread the
word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One large project which has become accessible through efforts of the
blind reaching out is Retroarch. An issue was created asking for
accessibility, and it was released in the very next version, and even
more work is being done to make even more games accessible. Open source
collaboration is great for even more than just programming. See projects
I'm working on, all text, on &lt;a href="https://devinprater.github.io/about/"&gt;the About page of my original
blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another bit of news is that GTK, a way for programs to be displayed
and written, has had a
&lt;a href="https://blog.gtk.org/2020/02/17/gtk-hackfest-2020-roadmap-and-accessibility/"&gt;Hackfest&lt;/a&gt;,
where accessibility was extensively discussed. It is hoped that this means
that accessibility will become a larger issue in Linux, and that blind
people will one day be able to use Linux as confidently as they use
Windows and Mac now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time goes by, I find myself drawn to open source. its promise of a
better way of making software, the community of helpful people, and the
freedom give me hope. While the Linux operating system does not come
close to satisfying the hope I have for accessibility, programs and
initiatives on top of Windows and Mac have thrived. While the poor
accessibility statement of the GNU project shows that the community at
large does not yet care much about accessibility, the community of blind
people working for our own future, rather than that of a corporation,
gives me hope of a bright future of digital accessibility for blind
people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What do you think, reader? Does open source call to you as well? Do you
just use whatever system you're given? Have you made peace with Linux's
shortcomings around accessibility? Please, let me know. I am glad to
receive feedback. If you'd like, you may even suggest, via email or
Twitter, articles for which you feel passionate about that need
coverage. I will consider all that you send me, and thank you for
reading.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>advocacy</category><category>blindness</category><category>open-source</category><guid>https://devinprater.github.io/posts/2020-02-16-open-source-blindness/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 20:11:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Advocacy of open source software</title><link>https://devinprater.github.io/posts/2020-01-20-advocacy-of-open-source-software/</link><dc:creator>Devin Prater</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’ll detail my experiences of advocating for
accessibility in open source software, why it is important, and how
others can help. I’ve not been doing it for long, but at least now,
I’ve done a bit. I’ll also touch upon why I think open source
software, on all operating systems, is important, and what closed
source and closed feedback systems cannot offer, which open source
grants. On the other hand, there are things which closed source
somewhat grants, but which has faltered slightly in recent days. I
will attempt to denote what is fact and what is opinion, this goes for
any post of a commentary of informative nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Appeal of Open Source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source, or free software, basically means that a person can view
and change the source code of software that they download or own.
While this doesn’t mean much to users, it does mean that many
different people can work on a project to make it better. This has no
value on its own, see the "heartbleed" &lt;a href="http://heartbleed.com"&gt;SSL
bug&lt;/a&gt; and its
&lt;a href="https://www.securityweek.com/evolution-openssl-security-after-heartbleed"&gt;Aftermath&lt;/a&gt;,
but as with SSL, things can obviously improve when given an incentive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, open source technology is used in many closed source
operating systems. For example, the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/liblouis/liblouis"&gt;Liblouis&lt;/a&gt; braille tables are
used in
&lt;a href="https://www.applevis.com/blog/whats-new-ios-13-accessibility-individuals-who-are-blind-or-deaf-blind"&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.applevis.com/blog/new-features-changes-improvements-and-bugs-macos-catalina-blind-and-low-vision-users"&gt;macOS&lt;/a&gt;,
and most Linux distributions through &lt;a href="https://brltty.app"&gt;BRLTTY&lt;/a&gt;.
While the software is not perfect, it is often made for more than one
operating system, has a helpful community of users, and, greatest for
accessibility, developers who are more likely to consider
accessibility. This is greatly improved with platforms for open source
development, like Github and Gitlab, which allow users to post
"issues" on projects, including accessibility ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Appeal of Closed Source&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People like getting paid. I should know, as a working blind person who
does love getting paid for time and effort well spent. People love
keeping things hidden while being worked on. I wouldn’t want a reader
reading an incomplete blog post, after all, and spreading the word
that "Devin just kind of wrote a few words and that’s all I got. from
the blog." People love being able to claim their work as theirs,
instead of having to share the credits with other people or companies.
I don’t have direct experience with this, because I need all the help
I can get, but in my opinion, it is a factor in choosing to create on
your own, as a user or a company. Another great thing about closed
source is that your competitors can’t copy what you’re doing, as you
do it, and when you’re an important company, with allegiance to your
shareholders, you must do anything to keep making money. But, what
about accessibility?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Open Source Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility of open source projects vary a lot. For example, before
Retroarch was &lt;a href="https://www.libretro.com/index.php/retroarch-1-8-2-coming-soon-accessibility-features-for-blind-people/"&gt;made
accessible&lt;/a&gt;,
its interface was not usable by blind people. Now, though, I can use
it easily. However, current versions of the &lt;a href="https://kde.org/plasma-desktop"&gt;KDE Plasma
desktop&lt;/a&gt; do not work well with &lt;a href="https://help.gnome.org/users/orca/stable/"&gt;the
Orca screen reader&lt;/a&gt;. The
following quote is from the release notes for KDE’s latest desktop
version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KDE is an international technology team that creates free and open
source software for desktop and portable computing. Among KDE's
products are a modern desktop system for Linux and UNIX platforms,
comprehensive office productivity and groupware suites and hundreds
of software titles in many categories including Internet and web
applications, multimedia, entertainment, educational, graphics and
software development. KDE software is translated into more than 60
languages and is built with ease of use and modern accessibility
principles in mind. KDE's full-featured applications run natively on
Linux, BSD, Solaris, Windows and Mac OS X.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- &lt;a href="https://kde.org/announcements/plasma-5.17.0.php"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Modern accessibility principals," you say? In my opinion, we seem to
be talking about different definitions of "accessibility." Yes, there
are multiple definitions. One is accessibility in the sense of being
able to be accessed, another is the ability to be found, and the
ability of being easy to deal with. As stated in the About section of
the site, I use accessibility to mean being able to be used
&lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; by blind people. This carries with it the implication
that every single function, and all needed visual information, can be
conveyed to a blind person in order for it to be accessible. This
rules out the "good enough" approach that so many blind people accept
as the status quo. Luckily for blind people who would love to use KDE,
there is &lt;a href="https://blogs.fsfe.org/gladhorn/2018/10/14/screen-reader-accessibility-for-the-plasma-desktop/"&gt;work being
done&lt;/a&gt;
on this issue. Gnu, the project behind much of Linux, also has an
&lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/accessibility/"&gt;accessibility statement&lt;/a&gt;, which
does seem to be very out of date, as it references flash player and
Silverlight, which are no longer in common use, and does not reference
Apple’s iOS, Google’s Android, and other modern technologies which are
not open source, but which include assistive technologies. I encourage every adventurous blind person to make
themselves available for testing open source software and operating
systems; user testing was mentioned by the KDE team as something blind
people could do to help.
Believe me, having an operating system which is a "joy to use" is a
&lt;em&gt;dream&lt;/em&gt; of mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gnome, and Mate, accessibility are okay, but they do not come close to
the accessibility of Windows and Mac systems. For a good example, if
you press Alt + F1 in Gnome, and probably Mate too, you may only hear
"window." Advanced users will know to type something in Gnome, or use
the Arrow Keys in Mate, but regular users should not have to learn to
hunt around due to bad accessibility, and the fact that less
technically inclined users use Linux is a testament to blind people’s
ingenuity and ability to adapt, rather than the accessibility of the
platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source accessibility is so hit and miss because there are so many
standards. There is the GTK framework for building graphical apps,
which does have some accessibility support, but developers must label
the items in their programs with text. There is the QT framework,
which seems to have more poor accessibility support. Basically,
developers can do anything they want, which is good for freedom, but
often is not great for accessibility. Also, much of the community has
not heard of accessibility practices, do not know that blind people
use computers, or think that we must use braille interfaces to
interact with computers and digital devices. This is a failure on our
part, as we do not "get out there" on the Internet enough. With the
advent of an &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/DystopiaForReddit/"&gt;accessible Reddit
client&lt;/a&gt;, this may begin
to change. Further work must be done to give blind users an accessible
Reddit interface on the web for users to use on computers, not
iPhones. However, Github is very accessible, and there is nothing
stopping one from submitting issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Closed Source Accessibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Okay but what about Windows? And Apple? You like Apple, right?"
Basically, it’s hard to tell. Software doesn’t write itself, it is
written, for now, by people. People can make mistakes, ignore
guidelines, or simply not care about accessibility. However, those
guidelines do exist, and are usually one standard, like the iOS
accessibility standard. This means that companies can develop
accessible software easily, and are held accountable by managers to
uphold accessibility. But, even the best of accessible companies do
not always do the right thing. Apple, for example, has created two
services, Apple Arcade and Apple Research. Apple Arcade contains &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;
games which a blind gamer can play without expending much more effort
than a sighted gamer. Apple Research contains some questions with
answer buttons which are not labeled, or cannot be activated. Does
Apple think that blind people do not want to game, or that we don’t
care about our hearing, heart, or for women, their reproductive
health? Apple has also created Swift Playgrounds, an app for children
to learn to code. This is accessible. But what about adults? Shouldn’t
blind adults, who are usually technically inclined enough, be given a
chance to learn to code? I’ll probably rant about this in a future
article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has been on an accessibility journey for a few years now,
but even they have a few problems. First, the voices in Windows 10 are
poor for screen reading tasks. They pause way too long at the end of
clauses and sentences, leading me, at least, to press Down Arrow to
move to the next line before the last line was actually done being
spoken, all because it paused just long enough to make me think that
there was no more text to speak. Microsoft’s XBox Game Pass is great,
but I could not find any accessible games in the free rotations. Sure,
there’s Killer Instinct that many blind people can enjoy playing, but
I found it not only inaccessible, as the menus do not speak, but
boring, as the characters all seemed to simply do the same thing. I
know that games do not have to be accessible to be fun, but I expect
companies who showcase games, like Apple with Arcade, to have at least
one accessible game for blind people to enjoy. And I also know that
neither Apple nor Microsoft makes these games, but they do choose to
advertise them, endorse them even, and it shows that, for Apple Arcade
at least, video games are not something which they expect blind people
to play. Microsoft is proving them wrong, with the
release of Halo with screen reader usability in menus, and the
possibility that the new Halo game will be accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another problem with Microsoft is that not all of their teams are
onboard. Like Apple with Arcade and Research, Microsoft has the
Rewards team. Their quizzes require one to move items around to
reorder answers to get the quiz correct. This may be easy, and perhaps
fun, for sighted people, but are simply frustrating for blind people.
Other problems include the release of the new Microsoft Edge, which,
for most users of screen readers, require that the user turn off UI
Automation in order to read some items on the web. Otherwise, if
Microsoft’s upcoming foldable phone comes with greatly enhanced
accessibility relative to pure Android, and the Narrator screen
reader, optimized and made great and enjoyable for a mobile
experience, I think that Microsoft could take plenty of market share back
from Apple of mobile phone users. They already have most general
purpose computer users who are blind, so taking from Apple would be a
huge win for them regarding accessibility. But, on that, we’ll have to
wait and see how far Microsoft takes their commitment to
accessibility. The more cynical side of me says that Microsoft will
simply slap Android on a folding phone and release it, because why
fight Apple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reporting Bugs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do to make accessibility better? Just about all open
source software, including the stuff making up this blog, is hosted on
Github. Just about all companies, of closed source software, claim to
want your feedback. So, I recommend giving them any feedback you have.
I know that giving feedback to Apple is like throwing $100 bills into
the ocean, giving your valuable time to something which may offer no
results, and just gives you the robotic "thanks" message. I know that
sometimes talking to Microsoft’s accessibility team may seem
unproductive, because they lead you from Twitter to one of a number of
feedback locations. I know that feedback to open source software
projects may take a lot of time and explaining and promoting
accessibility to a community which has never considered it before, but
it all may help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a great, and successful, Github issue regarding accessibility, see
&lt;a href="https://github.com/libretro/RetroArch/issues/9661"&gt;this issue on accessibility of
Retroarch&lt;/a&gt;. You can
see that I approached the Retroarch team respectfully, with knowledge
of basic accessibility and computer terminology. Note that I gave what
should happen, what is happening, and what can be done to fix the
problem. As the saying goes, if you do not contribute to a solution to
a problem, you are a part of the problem. Blind people will need to
remember to give solutions, not just whine about something not working
and can’t play Poke A Man like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, share links to your feedback with other blind people who can
vote, thumb up, or comment on it. Remember, if you do comment, please
remember that feedback does not net instant results. I’m still waiting
on &lt;a href="https://github.com/webcamoid/webcamoid/issues/211"&gt;Webcamoid to have an accessible
interface&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/libretro/RetroArch/issues/9920"&gt;Adding Active Accessibility into Games for
Retroarch&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://github.com/rileytestut/DeltaCore/issues/13"&gt;This Delta
issue&lt;/a&gt;. But, at
least I’ll know when something changes, and I could even &lt;a href="https://www.bountysource.com"&gt;Pay for
features to be implemented&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is opposed to the closed source model, where feedback is "passed
on to the team," or you are thanked, by your iPhone, for your
feedback, but do not hear anything back from developers, and you most
definitely can not pay for specific features to be worked on, or
donate to projects that you feel deserve it. You must hope and have
faith that large companies with more than one billion users cares
enough to hear you. For perspective, if every blind person stopped
using an iPhone, Apple would not miss many lost sales, compared to the
billions of sighted users. However, the engineers who work on iOS
accessibility are people too, with deadlines, lives, and feelings, and
we should also respect that they are probably tightly restricted in
answering feedback, fixing bugs, and creating new, exciting features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for me, I will continue to support open source software. I’ll keep
using this mac and iPhone because they work the best for me and what I
do for work and writing. But, believe me, when something better comes
along, I’ll jump ship quickly. As blind people, I feel, we cannot
afford to develop brand loyalty. Apple, Microsoft, or Google, I think,
could
drop accessibility tomorrow, and there we’d be, left in the cold. I
highly doubt they will. They may let it lie stagnant, but they
probably won’t remove it. I do not write this to scare you in the
least, but to make you think about how much control you actually have
over what you use, how companies and developers view us, and how we
can improve the situation for ourselves. if sighted people notice a
bug or want a feature in iOS or Windows, they can gather their tech
press and pressure Apple or Microsoft. If we find an accessibility
bug, do we have enough clout, or unity, to pressure these companies?
Writing feedback, testing software, trying new things, writing guides
and fixing documentation, or, if able, translating software into other
languages are all things that &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; blind person can do. I’m not
saying that I’m perfect at any of this. I just think that we as a
community can grow tremendously if we strike out from our comfortable
Windows PC’s, Microsoft Word, audio games, TeamTalk, and old speech
synthesizers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll give some projects you could try out and give feedback on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;- &lt;a href="https://marcozehe.de/2019/12/20/how-to-get-around-matrix-and-riot-with-a-screen-reader/"&gt;Riot IM, for text and voice chatting in groups, like TeamTalk&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blindness</category><category>open-source</category><guid>https://devinprater.github.io/posts/2020-01-20-advocacy-of-open-source-software/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>